BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH

(Last updated: 20/04/2020)

Miguel Tábuas Pereira, MD, PhD Candidate

Consultant Neurologist and Clinical Researcher Centro Hospitalar e Universitário de Coimbra Praceta Prof. Mota Pinto, 3000-075, Coimbra, Portugal Date of Birth: 19/09/1987

Head of the Memory Clinic

miguelatcp@gmail.com

+351 913 166 131







PHOTO



A. EDUCATION/TRAINING:

INSTITUTION AND LOCATION	DEGREE	YEAR(s)	FIELD OF STUDY
University of Coimbra	MD	2005-2011	Medicine
University College of London	PgDip	2017- ongoing	Clinical Neurology
University of Coimbra	PhD	2018- ongoing	Neuroscience

B. POSITIONS AND HONORS

Positions and Employment

2018 Neurologist, Coimbra University Hospital

2013 Neurology Residency, Coimbra University Hospital

Other Experience and Professional Memberships

2016 to date – Member of the Higher Cortical Functions Scientific Panel of the European Academy of Neurology (EAN)

2016 to date - Member of the Education Committee of the EAN

Honors

2017 Winner of the 1st Neurology Tournament (Portuguese Society of Neurology)

2005 Gold Medal in the Ibero-America Physic Olympiads

2004 Bronze Medal in the San Paolo Mathematics Olympiads

- 1. Faster Cortical Thinning and Surface Area Loss in Presymptomatic and Symptomatic C9orf72 Repeat Expansion Adult Carriers. Le Blanc G, Pomerleau VJ, McCarthy J, et al. (including Tábuas-Pereira M). Ann Neurol. 2020.
- 2. Neuronal Pentraxin 2: A Synapse-Derived CSF Biomarker in Genetic Frontotemporal Dementia. Van der Ende EL; Xiao M, Xu D, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2020.
- 3. Alzheimer's Disease Genetics: Review of Novel Loci Associated with Disease. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Santana I, Guerreiro R, Bras J. Curr Genet Med Rep 2020.
- 4. **Two sisters with myoclonus and ataxia**. <u>Pereira M</u>, Durães J, Carmo, MC. Pract Neurol. 2020.
- 5. Plasma glial fibrillary acidic protein is raised in progranulin-associated frontotemporal dementia. Heller C, Foiani MS, Moore K, Convery R, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2020.
- 6. Headache intensity is associated with increased white matter lesion burden in CADASIL patients. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Varela R, Beato-Coelho J, et al. J Clin Neurosci. 2020.
- 7. Single Word Repetition Predicts Long-Term Outcome of Aphasia Caused by an Ischemic Stroke. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Beato-Coelho J, Ribeiro J, Nogueira AR, Cruz L, Silva F, Sargento-Freitas J, Cordeiro G, Santana I. J Stroke Cerebrovasc Dis. 2020.
- 8. A worldwide cohort study of age at symptom onset and death and disease duration in genetic frontotemporal dementia. Moore KM, Nicholas J, Grossman M, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). Lancet Neurology. 2020.
- 9. Lower CSF Amyloid-Beta₁₋₄₂ Predicts a Higher Mortality Rate in Frontotemporal Dementia. Vieira D, Durães J, Baldeiras I, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). Diagnostics (Basel). 2019.
- 10. **Serum Neurofilament Light Chain in Genetic Frontotemporal Dementia: A Longitudinal, Multicentre Cohort Study.** Van der Ende EL, Meeter LH, Poos JM, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). Lancet Neurol. 2019.
- 11. Increased CSF tau is associated with a higher risk of seizures in patients with Alzheimer's disease. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Durães J, Lopes J, et al. Epilepsy Behav. 2019.
- 12. Education modulates brain maintenance in presymptomatic frontotemporal dementia. Gazzina S, Grassi M, Premi E, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2019.
- 13. Functional network resilience to pathology in presymptomatic genetic frontotemporal dementia. Rittman T, Borchert R, Jones S, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). Neurobiol Aging. 2019
- 14. The inner fluctuations of the brain in presymptomatic Frontotemporal Dementia: The chronnectome fingerprint. Premi E, Calhoun VD, Diano M, et al. (including <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>). Neuroimage. 2019
- 15. Increased risk of melanoma in C9ORF72 repeat expansion carriers: A case-

- **control study.** <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Almendra L, Almeida MR, Durães J, Pinho A, Matos A, Negrão L, Geraldo A, Santana I. Muscle Nerve. 2019
- 16. Discriminative capacity and construct validity of the Clock Drawing Test in Mild Cognitive Impairment and Alzheimer's disease. Duro D, Freitas S, <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Santiago B, Botelho MA, Santana I. Clin Neuropsychol. 2018
- 17. The Head Turning Sign in Dementia and Mild Cognitive Impairment: Its Relationship to Cognition, Behavior, and Cerebrospinal Fluid Biomarkers. Durães J*, Tábuas-Pereira M*, Araújo R, Duro D, Baldeiras I, Santiago B, Santana I. Dement Geriatr Cogn Disord. 2018 Aug 9;46(1-2):42-49. doi: 10.1159/000486531.
- 18. Aphasia Rapid Test: Translation, Adaptation and Validation Studies for the Portuguese Population. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Freitas S, Beato-Coelho J, et al. Acta Med Port. 2018 May 30;31(5):265-271. doi: 10.20344/amp.9090
- 19. Validity and Clinical Utility of Different Clock Drawing Test Scoring Systems in Multiple Forms of Dementia. Duro D, <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Freitas S, Santiago B, Botelho MA, Santana I. J Geriatr Psychiatry Neurol. 2018 Jan 1:891988718774432. doi: 10.1177/0891988718774432.
- 20. Underlying Biological Processes in Mild Cognitive Impairment: Amyloidosis Versus Neurodegeneration. Santana I, Baldeiras I, Santiago B, Duro D, Freitas S, Pereira MT, Almeida MR, Oliveira CR. J Alzheimers Dis. 2018 Mar 16. doi: 10.3233/JAD-179908.
- 21. Addition of the Aβ42/40 ratio to the cerebrospinal fluid biomarker profile increases the predictive value for underlying Alzheimer's disease dementia in mild cognitive impairment. Baldeiras I, Santana I, Leitão MJ, Gens H, Pascoal R, <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Beato-Coelho J, Duro D, Almeida MR, Oliveira CR. Alzheimers Res Ther. 2018 Mar 20;10(1):33. doi: 10.1186/s13195-018-0362-2.
- 22. Alzheimer's Disease Assessment Scale Cognitive Subscale (ADAS-Cog): Normative Data for the Portuguese Population. Nogueira J, Freitas S, Duro D, <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Guerreiro M, Almeida J, Santana I. Acta Med Port. 2018 Feb 28;31(2):94-100. doi: 10.20344/amp.8859. Epub 2018 Feb 28.
- 23. Intracranial Internal Carotid Artery Wall Calcification in Ischemic Strokes Treated with Thrombolysis. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Sargento-Freitas J, Silva F, Parra J, Mendes P, Seara V, Mesquita M, Baptista M, Cordeiro G, Cunha L. Eur Neurol. 2018;79(1-2):21-26. doi: 10.1159/000477901. Epub 2017 Nov 13.
- 24. Clinical Reasoning: A 55-year-old man with rapidly progressive dementia and parkinsonism
- <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Santana I, Santo GC. Neurology. 2017 Oct 10;89(15):e182-e187. doi: 10.1212/WNL.00000000004495. Epub 2017 Oct 9.
- 25. **Neurosonology Accuracy for Isolated Acute Vestibular Syndromes**. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Sargento-Freitas J, Isidoro L, Silva F, Galego O, Nunes C, Cordeiro G, Cunha L. J Ultrasound Med. 2017 Dec;36(12):2545-2550. doi: 10.1002/jum.14301. Epub 2017 Jul 10.
- 26. European Academy of Neurology Resident and Research Fellow Section: innovations and future direction in 2017. Papp V, Klingelhoefer L, Zis P, Melis M, <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Macerollo A, Sauerbier A. Eur J Neurol. 2017 Sep;24(9):e51-e53. doi: 10.1111/ene.13352. Epub 2017 Jun 21.

- 27. Association between butyrylcholinesterase and cerebrospinal fluid biomarkers in Alzheimer's disease patients. Gabriel AJ, Almeida MR, Ribeiro MH, Durães J, <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Pinheiro AC, Pascoal R, Santana I, Baldeiras I. Neurosci Lett. 2017 Feb 22;641:101-106. doi: 10.1016/j.neulet.2017.01.036. Epub 2017 Jan 17.
- 28. Tremor Frequency Assessment by iPhone® Applications: Correlation with EMG Analysis. Araújo R, <u>Tábuas-Pereira</u> M, Almendra L, Ribeiro J, Arenga M, Negrão L, Matos A, Morgadinho A, Januário C. J Parkinsons Dis. 2016 Oct 19;6(4):717-72.
- 29. **Prosopagnosia as the Presenting Symptom of Whipple Disease.** <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Vicente M, Coelho F, Santana I. Cogn Behav Neurol. 2016 Jun;29(2):100-6. doi: 10.1097/WNN.000000000000001.
- 30. Prognosis of Early-Onset vs. Late-Onset Mild Cognitive Impairment: Comparison of Conversion Rates and Its Predictors. <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Baldeiras I, Duro D, Santiago B, Ribeiro MH, Leitão MJ, Oliveira C, Santana I. Geriatrics (Basel). 2016
- 31. [Mini-Mental State Examination: Screening and Diagnosis of Cognitive Decline, Using New Normative Data]. Santana I, Duro D, Lemos R, Costa V, Pereira M, Simões MR, Freitas S. Acta Med Port. 2016.
- 32. **Biparietal variant of Alzheimer's disease: a rare presentation of a common disease.** Marques IB, <u>Tábuas-Pereira M</u>, Milheiro M, Santana I. BMJ Case Rep. 2015 Jan 5;2015. pii: bcr2014207011. doi: 10.1136/bcr-2014-207011.

D. RESEARCH SUPPORT (LAST 5 YEARS):

Tecnifar Grant "The relationship between white matter lesions with pain sensitivity dysregulation in patients with migraine". (2015) (PI: Miguel Tábuas-Pereira)

E. BIBLIOMETRIC INDICATORS

Miguel Tábuas-Pereira | Miguel Pereira | Tábuas-Pereira, M. [ORCID ID | https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3988-614X | SCOPUS ID: 56493155900]

[Google scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=zu-bUQkAAAAJ&hl=pt-PT]

- 1. Total number of citations (google scholar): 95
- 2. h factor (google scholar): 5
- 3. Cumulative impact factor: 156.477
- 4. Number of papers with impact factor over 7 during the last 5 years: 7
- 5. Number and impact of papers as corresponding or last author during the last 5 years: **12**, **27**.**809**